[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
SE-R SC radio is brought to you by the I
computer society and by It software
Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Gavin Henry and
today my guest is sha marotti Sean is
the author of machine learning in Elixir
and genetic algorithms in elixir both
published by the pragmatic bookshelf
co-creator of the NX library and creator
of the axon deep learning framework
Sean's interests include mathematics
machine learning and artificial
intelligence Sean welcome to software
engineering radio is there anything I
missed that you'd like to add no I think
that's great thanks for having me
excellent we're going to have a chat
about what deep learning means today
what axent is and why it was created and
finally go through an anomaly fraud
detection example using Axon so deep
learning sea what is it today yeah deep
learning I would say is best described
as a way to learn hierarchical
representations of inputs so it's
essentially a composition of functions
with learned parameters and that's
really a fancy way to say it's a bunch
of linear algebra chained together and
the idea is that you can take an input
and then transform that input into
structured representations so for
example exle if you give an image of a
dog a deep learning model can learn to
extract say edges from that dog in one
layer and then extract colors from that
dog in another layer and then it learns
to take those structured representations
and use them to classify the image as
say a cat or a dog or an apple or an
orange so it's really just a fancy way
to say linear algebra and what does
Elixir bring to this problem space yeah
so Elixir as a lang language offers a
lot in my opinion so the thing that
really drew me in is that Elixir I think
is a very beautiful language it's a way
to write really idiomatic functional
programs and when you're dealing with
complex mathematics I think it
simplifies a lot of things math is
really well expressed functionally in my
opinion another thing that it offers is
it's built on top of the airline VM
which has I would say like 30 years of
deployment success it's really a super
powerful tool for building scalable
fault tolerant applications we have some
advantages over say like python
especially when dealing with problems
that require concurrency and other
things so really Elixir as a language
offers a lot to the machine learning
space we'll dig in in the next section
history of arxon and why you created it
but why do we need deep learning versus
traditional machine learning yeah I
think that's a good question I think to
start it's better to answer the question
why we need machine learning in general
so back in I would say like like the '
50s when artificial intelligence was a
very new nent field there was this big
Conference of like academics Marvin
Minsky Allen Turing some of the more
famous academics you can think of
attended where they all wanted to decide
essentially how we can make machines
that think and the prevailing thought at
that time was that we could use formal
logic to encode a set of rules into
machines on how to reason how to think
about you know how to speak English how
to to take images and classify what they
are and the idea was really that you
could do this all with formal logic and
this kind of subset grew into what is
called now expert systems and that was
kind of the prevailing wisdom for quite
a long time I think there honestly are
still probably active projects where
they're trying to use formal logic to
encode very complex things into machines
and if you think of like languages like
prologue that's kind of something that
came out of this field now anyone who
speaks I would say say like English as a
second language can tell you why this is
maybe a very challenging problem because
English is one of those languages that
has a ton of exceptions and anytime you
try to encode something formally and you
run into these edge cases I would say
it's very difficult to do so so for
example if you think of like an image of
an orange or an image of an apple it's
difficult for you to describe in like an
if else statement style what makes that
image an apple or what makes that image
an orange and so we need to encode
things I would say probabilistically
because there are edge cases simple
rules are better than rigorous or
complex rules so for example it's much
simpler for me to say hey there's an 80%
chance that this picture is an orange or
there's an 80% chance like so let's say
this is a very popular example in Ian
goodfellow's book deep learning he says
if you try to say come up with a rule
for what birds fly your rule would start
as all birds fly except Penguins except
Young birds and then the rule goes on
and on when it's actually much simpler
to say all birds fly or 80% of birds fly
and you can kind of think of that as a
way to probabilistically encode that
rule there so that's kind of why we need
machine learning and machine learning in
general is not suitable for what we're
trying to do that's when deep learning
comes in that's correct so deep learning
comes in when you're dealing with what's
essentially called The Curse of
dimensionality so when you're dealing
with inputs that have a lot of
Dimensions or higher dimensional spaces
deep learning is really good at breaking
down these high dimensional spaces these
very complex problems into structured
representations that that it can then
use to create these probabilistic or
uncertain rules deep learning really
thrives in areas where like feature
engineering is really difficult so a
good great example again is when dealing
with images or computer vision
especially is like one of the classical
examples of deep learning shining well
for any traditional machine learning
methods we're overtaking traditional
machine learning methods early on in
that space and then large language
models are just another one where you
know there's a ton of examples of
natural language processing being very
difficult for someone to do feature
engineering on and deep learning kind of
blowing it away because you don't really
need to do any feature engineering at
all because you can take this higher
dimensional complex problem and break it
down into structured representations
that can then use to classify inputs and
outputs essentially so just to give a
brief example of the Orange is an apples
thing before we move on to the next
section how would you break down a
picture of an orange into what you've
already mentioned layers so ultimately
you can run it through algorithms or a
model I think they're the same thing
aren't they and then spit out a thing
that says this is 80% an orange yeah so
if you were to take that problem like a
picture of an orange and apply it in
like the traditional machine learning
sense right so let's say I have a
picture of an orange and I have pictures
of apples and I want a different
differentiate between the two of them so
in a traditional machine learning
problem what I would do is I would try
to come up with features that describe
the orange so I might pull together
pixels and and break down that image and
say you know if 90% of the pixels are
orange then this value over here is a
one and I would try to do some complex
fure engineering like that the color
orange you mean the color orange yeah
that's right yeah or like you know if
there's like this distribution of pixels
is red then it's an apple and I would
pass it into into something like a
support Vector machine or a linear
regression model that can't necessarily
deal with higher dimensional inputs and
then I would try my best to classify
that as an apple or an orange with
something like deep learning I can pass
that into a neural network which like I
said is just a composition of functions
and my composition of functions would
then transform those pixels that high
dimensional representation into a
learned representation so the idea that
neural networks learn like specific
features let's say that one layer learns
edges one layer learns colors is correct
and incorrect at the same time it's kind
of like at times neuron networks can be
a black box we don't necessarily know
what they're learning but we do know
that they learn useful representations
so then I would pass it into a neural
network and my neural network would
essentially transform those pixels into
something that it could then use to
classify that image so a layer in this
parament would be an equation or
function in Elixir that's right yeah so
we map layers directly to Elixir
functions so in like the pytorch and in
the python world that's really like a
pytorch module but in Elixir we map
layers directly to functions and to get
the first input to the function that
would be where you're deciding what part
of an image you could use to
differentiate things like the the curve
of the orange or the color or that type
of thing yep so I would take a numerical
representation of the image and then I
would pass that into my deep learning
model but one of the strengths is that I
don't necessarily need to make a ton of
choices about what images or what inputs
I pass into my deep learning model
because it does a really good job of
essentially doing that like sort of
discrimination that pre feature
engineering work for me okay before we
get deeper into this because I've got a
million questions what shouldn't deep
learning be used for CU people tend to
just grab it for everything at the
moment don't they cuz it's yeah I think
that's a good question it's a also a
difficult question like I think if you
take your consultency H off and just say
right yeah yeah so I think the problems
that deep learning shouldn't be used for
obviously are just like simple problems
you can solve with code I think people
have a tendency to reach for machine
learning when like simple rules will do
much better simple heuristics might do
much better so for example if I wanted
to classify like tweets as positive or
negative like maybe a simple rule is to
just look at emoji and if it has a happy
face then you know it's happy tweet and
if it has a frowny face it's a negative
tweet like there's a lot of examples in
the wild of just people being able to
come up with clever rules that do much
better than deep learning in some spaces
I think another example is like on the
fraud detection problem maybe I just
look for links with redirects in you
know if someone is sending like fishing
texts or fishing emails I'll just look
for links with redirects an email or a
text and then say hey that's spam we
regardless of if the link or if the
actual content is spammy just use that
as my heris that's just an example of
something where I can solve a problem
with a simple solution rather than deep
learning deep learning comes into the
equation when you need I would say a
higher level of of accuracy or higher
level of precision on some of these
problems excellent so I'm going to move
us on to talk about axom which you
co-created or that's correct yes so what
is ax and if you could just go through
that again
yeah axon is a deep learning framework
written in Elixir so we have a bunch of
different problems in the Elixir machine
learning ecosystem the base of all of
our projects is the NX project which a
lot of people if you're coming from the
python ecosystem can think of as numpy
NX is implements like a behavior for
interacting with tensors which are
multi-dimensional arrays in the machine
learning terminology and then axon is
built on top of NX operations and it
kind of takes away a lot of the
boilerplate of working with deep
learning models so it offers ways for
you to create neural networks to create
deep learning models and then to also
train them work with things like mixed
Precision work with pre-trained models
Etc so it takes away a lot of the boiler
plate that you would need now for people
getting introduced to the ecosystem you
don't necessarily need axon to do any
deep learning like you could write it
all on an X if you wanted to but axon
makes it easier for people to get
started why was it created there's a lot
of other open source tools out there
isn't there yeah so the project started
really I would say it was back in 2020 I
was finishing college and I got really
interested in machine learning
Frameworks and reverse engineering
things and I at the time had written
this book called genetic algorithms in
Elixir and Brian curella the CEO of
docyard which is an Elixir consultancy
that does a lot of Open Source work
reached out to me and said hey would you
be interested in working with Jose fim
on machine learning tools for The Elixir
ecosystem because his assumption was if
I knew about genetic algorithms those
sound a lot like machine learning
related and it's not necessarily the
case genetic algorithms are really just
a way to solve intractable optimization
problems with pseudo evolutionary
approaches and he just assumed that you
know maybe I would be interested in
doing that and at the time I absolutely
was because I had just graduated college
and I was looking for something to do
looking for something to work on and
somewhere to prove myself I would say
and what better opportunity than to work
work with Jose valim who created Elixir
and really built this ecosystem from the
ground up and so we started working on
the NX project and the project initially
started with us working on a project
called exla which is elixir bindings for
a linear algebra compiler called xlaa
from Google which is built into
tensorflow and that's what Jax is built
on top of and we got pretty far along in
that project and then kind of needed
something to prove that NX would be
useful so we thought you know at the
time deep learning was easily the most
popular and honestly probably less
popular than it is now which is crazy to
say because it was still crazy popular
then it was just pre- chaty PT and pre
some of these Foundation models that are
out and we really needed something to
prove that the projects would work so we
decided to build axon and axon was
really like the first exercise of what
we were building in NX I just did a show
with Jose fim on Life Book Elixir and
the complete machine learning ecosystem
so we do explore just for the listeners
there what NX is and all the different
parts like Bumblebee and axon and
Scholar as well so I'll refer people to
that because we're just going to focus
on the Deep learning part here there are
a few versions of axon as I understand
based on influences from other languages
why did it evolve yeah so it evolved for
I would say two reasons as I was writing
the Library I quickly realized that some
things were very difficult to express in
like the way you would Express them in
tensorflow and ptch which were like two
of the Frameworks I knew going into it
and the reason is that with Elixir
everything is immutable and so dealing
with immutability is challenging
especially when you're trying to
translate things from the python
ecosystem so I ended up kind of reading
a lot about other attempts at
implementing like functional deep
learning Frameworks one that comes comes
to mind is think. a which is I think by
the people that created Spacey which is
a natural language processing framework
in Python and I also looked at other
Inspirations from like has and other
ecosystems the other reason that axon
kind of evolved in the way it did is
just because I like enjoy tinkering with
different apis and coming up with unique
ways to do things but really A lot of
the inspiration is the core of the
framework is really very very similar to
something like Caris something like
pytorch ignite is is a training
framework in pytorch and that's because
I want the framework to feel familiar to
people coming from the python ecosystem
so if you are familiar with how to do
things in Caris then picking up axon
should just be very natural because it's
very very similar minus a few catches
with immutability and functional
programming yeah it's really difficult
creating anything to get the interfaces
and the apis and the function names
correct so if you can borrow that from
another language and save and brain
space is a good way to go isn't it
exactly yeah so I figured if we could
reduce like the cognitive load or the
time it takes for someone to transition
from other ecosystems then we could do
really really well and elixir as a
language being a functional programming
language is already unfamiliar for
people coming from like mutable
languages and imperative programming
languages like python so doing anything
we could to make the transition easier I
think was very important from the start
what does axon use from the Elixir
machine learning ecosystem did just
mention that show 588 will have more but
just if we can refresh yeah so axon is
built on top of NX we also have a
library called Polaris which is a
library of optimizers inspired by the
Opex project in the python ecosystem
those are the only two projects really
that it relies on we tried to kind of
have a minimal dependency approach where
you know we're not bringing in a ton of
of libraries only kind of like the
foundational things that you need and
then you can optionally bring in a
library called exla which is for GPU
acceleration if you want to use it and
most people are going to want to do that
because otherwise you're going to be
using the pure Elixir implementation of
a lot of the NX functions and it's going
to be very slow so that would be like
when a language has a C library to speed
things up potentially exactly yeah so we
have a bunch of these compilers and
backends that I'm sure you get into in
that episode and that kind of
accelerates things for us excellent you
mentioned optimizing blurting models we
did an episode with William Falcon
episode 549 on that which I'll refer
listeners to is that optimizing the
learning or the inputs or how do you
define that yeah he is the pie torch
lightning guy right that's right yeah
pretty familiar because yeah I spent a
lot of time looking at pytorch lightning
as well when designing axon so when I
refer to optimization here I'm talking
about gradient-based optimization or
stochastic gradient descent so these are
implementations of like deep learning
optimizers like the atom op Optimizer
and you know traditional SGD and then
RMS prop and some other ones out there
not necessarily on like optimizing in
terms of memory optimization and then
like performance optimization now I've
just finished pretty much most of your
book that's available to read at the
women and if I remember correctly I'm
going to have a go here gradient descent
is is the example where you're trying to
measure the depth of an ocean and then
you're going left and right and the next
measurement you take if that's deeper
than the next one then you know to go
that way sort of thing yeah exactly
that's my sort of like simplified
explanation of gradient descent can you
say it instead of me I'm sure you do a
bad job yeah yeah so the way I like to
describe gradient descent is you get
dropped in a random point in the ocean
or some Lake and you have just a depth
finder you don't have a map and you want
to find the deepest point in the ocean
so what you do is you take measurements
of the depth all around you and then
then you move in the direction of
steepest descent or you move basically
to the next spot that brings you to a
deeper point in the ocean and you kind
of follow this greedy approach until you
reach a point where everywhere around
you is at a higher elevation or higher
depth than where you started and if you
follow this approach it's kind of a
greedy approach but you'll essentially
end up at a point that's deeper than
where you started for sure but you know
it might not be the deepest point but
it's going to be a pretty deep part the
ocean or the lake and that's kind of in
a way how gradient descent works as well
like we can't prove necessarily that
wherever your loss function which is a
way to measure how good deep learning
models do that your loss function when
optimized through gradient descent has
actually reached an optimal point or
like the actual minimum of that loss but
if you reach a point that's small enough
or deep enough then it's the model that
you're using is going to be good enough
in a way cool well let's try and scoop
all this up and go through a practical
example with the remaining time we've
probably got about half an hour let's
see how we go so I've picked hopefully a
good example to do fraud detection with
axon so that could be should we do
credit card fraud or go with that yeah I
think credit card Fraud's good so when I
did a bit of research in the machine
Lear ecosystem in your book me and Jose
spoke about Bumblebee and get an
existing model which I did a search on a
hugging tree I gu hugging face yep
hugging face yeah I always say hugging
tree and there's things on there but I
just want to go from scratch with the A
on if we can yep y so at a high level
before we Define things and and drill
into things what would your workflow be
for detecting credit card fraud with a
on the first thing I would do is try to
find a viable data set and that would be
either an existing data set online or it
would be something derived from like
your company's data or some internal
data that you have access to that maybe
nobody else has access to so that would
be something where your customers
reported that there's been a transaction
they didn't make on their credit card
statement whether that's through credit
card details being stolen or they put
them into a fake website Etc they've
been compromised somewhere and of course
these people would have millions of
customers so they'd probably have a lot
of records that were fraud correct yeah
and then you would take features of
those of those transactions and that
would include like the price that you're
paying the merchant the location of
where the transaction was like if the
transaction is somewhere overseas and
you live in the US then obviously that's
kind of a red flag and then you would
take all these all these features and
then like you said people had they
reported like if it's fraud or not and
then you use that as kind of like your
true Benchmark or your true labels and
one of the things you're going to find
when you're working through this problem
is that it's a very unbalanced data set
so obviously when you're dealing with
like transactions especially credit card
transactions on the scale of like
Millions then you might run into like a
couple thousand that are actually
fraudulent it's not necessarily common
in that space it's not common for what
sorry yeah sorry so so what I'm trying
to say is if you have like millions of
transactions then a very small
percentage them are actually going to be
fraudulent so what you're going to end
up with is you're going to have a ton of
transactions that are legit and then
maybe like 1% or less than 1% of them
are going to be fraudulent transactions
and the phrase where they say rubbish in
and rubbish out it's extremely important
to get this good data and bad data
differentiated and then pick apart what
is of interest in that transaction like
you mentioned their location the amount
of the transaction is that a big
specific Topic in its own right to try
and do that was that not feature
engineering that you mentioned before
yeah I mean absolutely there's
definitely some feature engineering that
has to go into it and trying to identify
like what features are more likely to be
indicative of fraud than others and
that's just another word for in that Big
Blob ad Jason for example we're
interested in the IP address the amount
you know or their spend history that
type of thing exactly yeah so trying to
spend some time like with the features
is trying to spend a lot of time with
the data is is really more important
than going into and Diving right into
like design a model and training a model
and if it's a fairly common thing you're
trying to do there may be data sets that
have been predefined like you mentioned
that you could go and buy or go and use
you know that you trust exactly yeah so
someone might have already gone through
the trouble of Designing a data set for
you and you know labeling a data set and
in that case going with something like
that that's already kind of engineered
can save you a lot of time but maybe if
it's not as high quality as what you
would want then you need to do the work
yourself yeah cuz you might have have
your own data that you want to mix up
with that
exactly yep your organization's data is
is probably going to have a bit of a
different distribution than any other
organization's data so you need to be
mindful of that as well okay so now
we've got the data set and we've decided
on what features of that data we're
going to use what would be next yeah so
then the next thing I would do is I
would go about designing a model or
defining a model using axon and in this
case like fraud detection you can design
a relatively simple I would say feed
forward neural network to start and that
would probably be just a single function
that takes an input and then like
creates an axon model from that input
and then you can go about training it
and what what is a model in axon world
is that not an equation function rather
what does that mean the way that axon
represents models is through Elixir
structs so we build a data structure
that represents the the actual
computation that your model is going to
do and then when you go to get
predictions from that model or you go to
train that model we essentially
translate that data structure into an
actual function for you so it's kind of
like additional layers in a way away
from what the actual NX function looks
like but an axon basically what you
would do is you would just Define an
Elixir function and then you specify
your inputs using the axon do input
function
and then you go through some of the
other higher level axon layer definition
functions and that builds up that data
structure for you okay and axom would be
a good fit for this versus for example
I've got some notes Here logistic
regression or decision trees or support
Vector machines or random forests they
just seems to be Buzz words around
Elixir and machine learning so just
wondering if any of those is something
that we would use or yeah so in this
casee like you might find success with
some of those models and as a good
machine learning engineer like one thing
to do is to always test and continue to
evaluate different models against your
data set because the last thing you want
to do is like spend a bunch of money
training complex deep learning models
and maybe like a simple rule or a
simpler model blows that deep learning
model out of the water so one of the
things I like to do when I'm solving
machine learning problems like this is
basically create a competition and
evaluate three to four maybe five
different models against my data set and
figure out which one performs best in
terms of like accuracy precision and
then also which one is the cheapest and
fastest so the ones I just mentioned I
think they're from the traditional
machine learning world is that right
that's correct yep yeah and axom would
be yeah good so you do a sort of fight
offers as it were between traditional
and and deep learning if you've got the
time y that's right and in this case
something like fraud detection would
probably be pretty well suited for
something like this decision trees as
well and decision trees is just another
traditional machine learning algorithm
one of the advantages is that you can
kind of interpret them pretty easily you
know I would maybe train a decision tree
maybe train a logistic regression model
and then maybe also train a deep
learning model and then compare those
and find which one performs the best in
terms of acur scene Precision find which
one is the easiest to deploy and then
kind of go from
there engineering workflows can be a
mess from prioritizing Sprint tasks to
explaining technical diagrams you're
spending more time explaining work and
less time doing it mirro brings all your
work together seamlessly in one online
visual workspace create diagrams inl or
mermaid run sprints and create jir or
Azure tasks in Miro instantly go from
idea to action without switching to
different tools get your first three
boards free when you sign up today at
mirro.com slmp podcast that's m o o.com
SLP
podcast when I was doing my research for
this example because I was coming from
immediately the rule-based mindset of
how you try and Tackle when we spoke
about classifying an orange you'd say
right if it colors orange of circle
that's where I came to for the fraud bit
when I saw decision CHS I thought that
would be quite good because then you can
say right if it's not in the UK If it's
greater than2 200 or if they've done
five transactions in two minutes that
type of thing is that what a decision
tree is yeah that's basically how deis
work they essentially learn a bunch of
rules to partition a data set so like
you know one branch splits a data set
into some number of buckets and it kind
of grows from there the rules are
learned but you can actually like
physically interpret what those rules
are and so a lot of businesses prefer
decision trees because you can tie a
decision that was made by a model
directly to like the path that it took
okay and in this example we're
discussing could you run your data set
through one of these and then through a
deep learning model or would that be
pointless I wouldn't necessarily do that
I mean so in that case you be building
essentially what's called an ensemble
model but it would be a very strange
Ensemble model like a decision tree into
a deep learning model ensemble they're
pretty popular at least in like the
machine learning competition World
ensembles are essentially where you
train a bunch of models and then you
also take the predictions of those
models and train a model on the
predictions of those models and then
it's kind of like a Socratic method for
machine learning models yeah I was just
thinking about something to whittle
through the data set to get it sort of
sorted out and then shove it into the
the complex bit that would tidy up type
thing but I suppose that's what you do
on the data set to begin with isn't it
yeah and so that's like common in like
machine learning competitions because
you know like that extra
0.1% accuracy that you might get from
doing that really does matter that's the
difference between like winning and
losing the competition but in a
practical machine learning environment
it might not necessarily make sense if
it adds a bunch of additional like
computational complexity and then
complexity in terms of deployment to
your application just aside are there
deep learning competitions like you have
with when they're working on the latest
password hashing type thing to figure
out which way to go yeah so if you go on
kaggle there's actually a ton of active
competitions and they're not necessarily
like deep learning focused it's really
just open-ended can you use machine
learning to solve this problem so kaggle
has a ton of those and they've got a
leaderboard and everything and they they
pay out cash prizes so it's pretty fun
like I have done a few kagle
competitions not a ton recently because
I'm a little busy but it is a lot of fun
and if people want to use axon to
compete in some kagle competitions I
would be more than happy to help
excellent I'll put that that in the show
notes so the data we should start
collecting do we start with all of this
data we know is true and then move
forward to sort of live data that we
want to decide as fraud so what I'm
trying to ask an round about way there
when we do the feature engineering to
say what we're interested in is that
what we're always going to be collecting
to feed back into the thing that we
created to decide whether it's going to
be fraud or not yeah so typically
how you would solve this and it's a very
complex problem is like you would have a
baseline of like features that you
really care about but you would do some
sort of like Version Control and this is
where like the concept of feature stores
come in where you identify features to
train your Baseline models and then as
time goes on let's say like your data
science team identifies additional
features that you would like to add
maybe they take some other features away
then you would push those features out
to new models train those new models on
the new featur features and then go from
there but it becomes kind of like a
nightmare in a way like a really
challenging problem because you can
imagine if I have some versions that are
trained on like the snapshot of features
that I had on like today and then I have
another model that's trained on a
snapshot of features from like two weeks
ago then I have these like systems that
need to rectify okay like at this point
time I need to send these features to
this model and these new features to
this model so it becomes kind of like a
difficult problem but if you just like
only care about training like getting
this model over the fence today then you
would focus on just the features you
identify today and then you know
continue improving that model based on
those features but in like the machine
learning deployment space you're you're
always trying to identify new features
better features to improve the
performance of your model yeah I suppose
if some new type of data comes out of
the bank to help you classify something
you want to get that into your model or
a new model like you said straight away
exactly yeah so now we've got this data
what do we do with it we need to get it
into a form someone understands so we
built our model which is the function
yep so then what I would do is so let's
say we built our model we have our our
raw data now the next thing we need to
do is some sort of pre-processing to get
that data into a what we call a tensor
or an NX tensor and so how that will
probably be represented is I'll have
like a table maybe like a CSV that I can
load with something like explore which
is our data frame library that is built
on top of the Polar project from rust so
I have this data frame and that'll
represent like a table essentially of
inputs so each row of the table is one
transaction and each column represents a
feature and then I will transform that
into a tensor and then I can use that
tensor to create a or to pass into a
training pipeline an Explorer we
discussed that in show 58 that helps get
the data from the CSV file into an NX
sort of data structure is that correct
that's right yeah and then I I might use
Explorer to do other sort of like
pre-processing so for example if I have
categorical variables that are like
represented as strings like so for
example the country that a transaction
was placed in maybe that's represented
as like the iso country code and I want
to convert that into a number because NX
does not speak in like string or or any
of those complex data structures NX only
deals with numerical data types and so I
would convert that into a categorical
variable either using like one hot in
coding or maybe just like a single like
categorical number like 0 to 64 Z to
like
192 or however many countries there are
in the world so what would you do in our
example with an IP address would you
geolocate it to a country and then turn
that country into an integer from one to
what 256 main countries or something
yeah so something like an IP address I
might try to identify like the ISP that
that IP address originates from like I
think something like an IP address I
might try to enrich a little bit further
than just the IP address so take the ISP
maybe identify if it originates from a
VPN or not I think there might be
Services out there as well that like
identify like the percentage of
likelihood that an IP address is harmful
so maybe I take like that harm score and
use that as a feature rather than just
the IP address and you potentially could
let's say like break the IP address into
like a subnet so if I like look at an IP
address and say okay I'm going to have
all the SL 24s as categorical variables
then I can use that and then you can
kind of derive features in that way from
from an IP address so the original
feature of an IP address that you
selected at step one for example might
then become 10 different features
because you've broken that down in
enriched it exactly yeah so if you start
with an IP address you might do some
further work to create a ton of
different additional features that's a
massive job isn't it there's like a
common Trope in machine learning that
like 90% of the work is working with
data and then you know the fun stuff
like training the model and deploying a
model is not necessarily where you spend
a lot of your
time so the model it's a definition in a
text file isn't it it's not a physical
thing you would download as a binary or
you know we run this and it's spits out
a thing that we would import that's
right yeah so like the actual model
definition is is code and like when I'm
dealing with machine learning problems I
like to keep the model as code and then
like the parameters as as data so that
would be the only like that binary file
you would find we don't have any concept
of like model serialization in Elixir
because like I said my principle or my
my thought is that your your model is
code and should stay as code Okay so
we've got our data set let's say it's as
good as it can be we've got our model in
code we've cleaned it all up with
Explorer and got it into the format we
need and now we're feeding it into our
model what happens after that yeah so
then the next thing you would do is you
could would create a a training pipeline
or you would write a training Loop and
the training Loop is what's going to
apply that gradient descent that we
described earlier in the podcast on your
models parameters so it's going to take
the data set and then I'm going to pass
it through a definition of a supervised
train tring Loop in axon which uses the
axon do Loop API conveniently named and
that essentially implements like a
functional version of training Loops
it's if you're familiar with Elixir you
can think of it as like a giant en num.
ruce and that takes your data set and it
generates initial model parameters and
then it passes them or it goes through
the gradient descent process and
continuously updates your models
parameters for the number of iteration
you specify and it also tracks things
like metrics like say accuracy which in
this case is kind of a useless metric
for you to to track because like let's
say that I have this data set with a
million transactions and 99% of them are
legit then I can train a model and it'll
be 99% accurate by just saying that
every transaction is legit and as we
know that's not a very useful fraud
detection model because if it says
everything's legit then it's not going
to catch any actual like fraudulent
transactions so what I would really care
about here is like the Precision and
like the the number of true negatives
true positives false positives false
negatives that it catches and I would
track those and I would train this model
for you know let's say five epochs which
is kind of like the number of times
you've made it through your entire data
set or your model has seen your entire
data set and then on the end I would end
up with like a trained set of parameters
so just to summarize that bit see if
I've got it correct so we're feeding in
the data set that we know has got good
transactions and bad credit card
transactions and we're testing whether
it finds those is that correct with the
gradient
desent yeah so we are giving our model
examples of the like legit transactions
and the fraudulent transactions and then
we're having it grade whether or not a
transaction is fraudulent or legit and
then we are grading our models outputs
based on the actual labels that we have
and that produces a loss which is like
an objective function and then we apply
gradient descent to that objective
function to minimize that loss and then
we update our parameters in a way that
minimizes those loss oh it's finally
clicked okay I get it now so in the
tabular data we've got the CSV file
we've got all the features we're
interested in of the transaction and
then there'll be some column that says
this is fraud and this isn't that's
right yep so once that's analyzed the
probability if that's correct of what
we've decided that transaction is is
then checked against that column that
says it is or isn't fraud and that's how
we're training that's right exactly yeah
so our model is outputting like some
probability like let's say you know it
output 0.75 and that's a 75% chance that
this transaction is fraud and then I
look and that transactions actually
legit then I'll update my model
parameters according to whatever my
gradient algorithm says and so if you go
back to that like ocean example my loss
function like the values of the loss
function are the depth of that ocean and
so I'm trying to navigate this complex
loss function to find the deepest point
or the the minimal point in that loss
function and when you say you're looking
at that output is that another function
in axon or are you physically looking no
no so actually like I shouldn't say I'm
looking at it but it's like an automated
process so the actual training process
axon takes care of for you so that's the
training yeah so I was thinking there'
be a lot of data to look at and go no
that was right that was wrong yeah yeah
I guess you could do it by hand but cool
so this obviously dependent on the size
of the data set we would need to I mean
how do you go about resourcing this type
of task hardware-wise is that something
you're familiar with yeah so something
like this like the model you would train
would actually probably PR pretty
inexpensive and you could probably train
it on a commercial laptop and no like I
don't I guess I shouldn't speak because
I I don't have access to like a billion
transactions to see like how long it
would take to Crunch through them but
you could train a model pretty quickly
and there are like commercial and and
are also like open source fraud data
sets out there there's an example of a
credit card fraud data set on kaggle and
there's also one in the axon repository
that you can work through and the data
sets actually pretty small if you were
training like a larger model or you had
to go through a lot of data then you
would more than likely need access to a
GPU and you can either have one like on
Prem or if you you have Cloud resources
you can go and provision one in the
cloud and then axon if you use one of
the exla like backends or compilers then
it'll it'll just do the GPU acceleration
for you and the gpus are used because
they're good at processing a tenser of
data that's right yeah gpus have a lot
of like specialized kernels that can
process this information very
efficiently so I G answer what the
graphics cards used to display like a 3D
image or something in games and Etc yep
that kind of relationship is very useful
for deep learning practitioners so I've
got my head around the data set and you
know other than working through example
myself with the data set I get that that
could be something physical that you
download from third parties that spent a
lot of time and being sort of peer-
reviewed and things what sort of things
are you downloading from hugging face
then through bumblebee models hugging
face has in particular a lot of large
language models that you can download
for tasks like you know text
classification named entity recognition
like going to the transaction example
they might have like a named entity
recognition model that I could use to
pull the entities out of a transaction
description so I could maybe use that as
an additional feature for this like
fraud detection model like hey this
Merchant is Adidas and I know that
because I pulled that out of the
transaction description so that's just
an example of like one of the pre-train
models you might download from say
hugging face using bubblebee okay I just
understand what you're physically
downloading there so in our example for
fraud are we trying to classify a data a
ruin that CSV as fraud or we doing a
regression task as in we're trying to
reduce it to a yes or no that is fraud
yeah it depends on I guess what you want
your output to be so like one of the
things you always have to do in machine
learning is make a business decision on
the other end of it so a lot of like
machine learning tutorials will just
stop after you've trained the model and
that's not necessarily how it works in
practice because I need to actually get
that model to like a deployment and then
make a decision based on what my model
outputs so in this case if we want to
just detect fraud like yes no fraud then
it would be like a classification
problem and my outputs would be like a
zero for legit and then a one for fraud
but another thing I could do is like
maybe I assign a risk score to my actual
data set and that might be framed as a
regression task I would probably still
frame it as like a classification task
because I have access to labels that say
yes fraud no not fraud but it really
kind of depends on what your actual
business use case is so with regression
and a risk factor there when you
described how you detect whether it's an
orange or an apple you're kind of saying
I'm 80% sure it's an orange with
classification wouldn't that be one yes
it's an orange or zero it's no I'm a bit
confused between classification and
regression there yeah yeah so regression
is like dealing with quantitative
variables so like if I wanted to predict
say the price of a stock after a certain
amount of time that would be a
regression problem whereas if I'm
dealing with like qualitative variables
like yes fraud no fraud then I would be
dealing in
classifications okay perfect we touched
on the training part so we're getting
pretty close to winding up here but the
training part where we're I think you
said fine tuning the parameters to our
model is that what training is in this
example yeah fine tuning is often used
as like a terminology when working with
pre-trained models in this case case
we're we're really just like training
updating the parameters so we're
starting with like a baseline not a
pre-trained model we're we're starting
from some random initialization of
parameters and then updating them using
gradient descent but the process is
identical to what you would do when
dealing with like a fine-tuning you know
case okay I'm just probably using the
wrong words there so a pre-trained model
is probably like a function in Elixir
where you can give it different
parameters for it to do something and
your deciding what the output should be
yeah so the way the axon API works is
when you like kick off your training
Loop you call Ax on. loop. run and when
you are using a pre-trained model like
that takes an initial State like an En
num. ruw and when you're dealing with a
pre-trained model you would pass your
like pre-trained parameters into that
run whereas if you're dealing with just
training a model from scratch you would
pass an empty map because you don't have
any parameters to start with and that
would would be discovered through the
learning aspect later on exactly and
then the output of that would be your
models parameters okay and then if you
wanted at that point could you ship that
as a pre-trained model for someone else
to use or that just be always specific
to you yep so you could upload your
model parameters to hugging face and
then keep the code and for that model
definition and then like you would
update that maybe for the next a million
transactions you get in maybe you
retrain your model and or someone else
like wants to take that you can ship
that off for them so the parameters the
output of your learning so if we go back
to the example where you said you have
your model and code and we don't do like
in in Pearl or python you sort of freeze
the runtime state of the model as it
were are the parameters the runtime
state of all the learning that's
happened so far and you can just kind of
save that and pause that and pick it up
another day yep so then what I would do
is I would just serialize my parameter
map and then I would take the definition
of my model which is just code and you
would compile that and that that's kind
of like a way of saying like I I compile
that into a numerical definition it's
not it's a bad term if you're not able
to look directly at what's happening but
I would compile that and that would give
me a function for doing like predictions
and then I would pass my trained
parameters into that model prediction
function and then I can use that
prediction function to get outputs on
production data and that's the sort of
thing you could commit to your G
repository or something every now and
again to back it up production or
however you choose to do that exactly Y
and what do what would parameters look
like in front of me on the screen yeah
so you would see a Elixir map with like
names of layers and then a each layer
has its own parameter map with the name
of a parameter that maps to a tensor and
that that tensor would be a floating
Point tensor you would just see probably
a bunch of random numbers okay now
that's making a clear CLE pitch from my
head so hopefully it's helping out the
listeners okay so I'm going to move on
to some more general questions but still
around this example is there just one
type of neural network or we decided to
do the gradient descent is that the
standard way to do this or is that just
something applicable to for detection so
there are a ton of different types of
neural networks out there and the
decision of what architecture you use
kind of depends on the problem like
there is just like the basic feed
forward Nur Network that I would use for
for this one because it's cheap
performance-wise and will probably do
pretty well in terms of detecting fraud
and then there's like something like a
convolutional neural network which is
often used for images computer vision
problems there's recurrent neural
networks which are not as popular now
because of how popular Transformers are
there are Transformer models which are
massive massive language models or
massive models built on top of like
attention which is a type of I would say
it's kind of like a layer it's really a
technique for learning relationships
between sequences there's a ton of
different like architectures out there
and mention quite a few of them in your
book so I'll make sure we link to some
of your blog posts on docyard as well
yeah so I try to go through some of the
Baseline ones and then gradient descent
is like it's not the only way to train
in neur network but like it's the only
way you'll actually see and use in
practice okay so for this fraud
detention or anomaly detection example
are we trying to find anomaly in normal
transactions are we classifying
transactions as fraud based on training
or is that just the same thing and I've
made that really complicated it's
essentially the same exact problem just
framed in different ways so like the
anomaly detection portion would only be
I would say useful in like if I didn't
have labels on attached to my data so
like I would use something like an
unsupervised learning technique to do
anomaly detection to identify
transactions that might be fraudulent
but if I have access to the labels on
like a fraudulent transaction and not
fraudulent transaction then I would just
use like a traditional supervised
machine learning approach to solve that
problem because I have access to the
labels so that comes back to our initial
task which you said is the most
difficult part of all of this is the
quality of our data that we feed in so
if we spent more time to label fraud not
fraud we would do supervised learning
that's right yeah so I say like the best
machine learning companies are companies
that find a way to get their users or
their data like implicitly labeled
without much effort so like the best
example of this is the Google captas
where they ask you to identify that when
I was reading some of your stuff yep so
that's that's like the prime example of
like they have a way to it solves a
business problem for them and also they
get you to label their data for them and
there's third party services like the
Amazon Mechanical T isn't it where you
can pay people to label for you yep and
now like a common approach is to also
use something like gp4 to label data for
you and it might be cheaper and also
better than some of the like hand
labelers you would get because it's got
more information of what something would
be yep so if I was dealing with like a
text problem I would probably roll with
something like gp4 labels to save myself
some time and then bootstrap a model
from there and that's a Commercial
Services I would guess yep that's
correct so just to close off this
section quality of data is key spending
that extra time on on labeling whether
something is what you think it is will
help dictate where you want to go to
back up your data are the model which is
code and axon and how far you've learned
which is the parameters we can commit
that to a git repository but what would
that ongoing life cycle or operational
side of axon involved once we put this
workflow into production you know do we
move from CSV files to an API submitting
new data or do we pull that from a
database or you how do we do our Ops to
make sure it's doing what it should be
and say everything dies how did we
recover that type of normal thing do you
have any experience on that yeah it's
kind of an open-ended problem like the
first thing I would do is I would wrap
the model in what's called an NX serving
which is our like inference abstraction
so the way it works is it it it
implements like Dynamic batching so if
you have like a phoenix application then
it kind of handles the concurrency for
you so if you have like a million or
like let's say I'm getting 100 requests
at once overlapping within like a 10
millisecond time frame I don't want to
just call axon do predict you know like
my predict function on one of those
transactions at a time I actually want
to batch those so I can efficiently use
my CPU or gpus resources and so that's
what NX serving would take care of for
me and then I would probably implement
something like maybe I use like Oban
which is a job scheduling library and
elixir and that would continuously pull
data from whatever repository that I
have and then retrain my model and then
maybe it recommits it back to get or
maybe I use like S3 to store my models
parameters and I continuously pull the
most up-to-date model and and update my
serving in that way the beauty of the
Elixir and Airline ecosystem is that
there are like a hundred ways to solve
these like continuous deployment
problems and so no it's good to put
description on it so NX serving
kind of like your debounce in JavaScript
where it tries to smooth everything down
for you and the request you're talking
about there is real transactions coming
through from the bank where into your
API and you're trying to decide whether
it should go ahead or not Bas predicting
if it's fraud or potential fraud yeah
that's right and I'm not um super
familiar with the bounce so I I don't
know oh no it's just something that came
to mind it's where someone's typing a
keyboard and you can slow it down I
think maybe I've Mis that but it's a way
of smoothing out what's coming in yeah
in a way it's like a dynamic delay thing
yeah that's right so we would pull a new
data retrain the model to tweak our
parameters and then save that somewhere
every so often yep and it's kind of like
a a NeverEnding life cycle so you would
over time you end up like logging your
model's outputs you save some snapshot
of like the data that you have and then
you'll also obviously have people
reporting fraud happening in in real
time as well and you want to say like
hey did my model catch this did it not
catch this Why didn't it catch this and
those are the examples you're really
going to want to pay attention to like
the ones where your model classified it
as legit and it was actually fraud and
then the ones your model classified as
fraud when it was actually legit you can
have some workow that cleans that up and
alerts someone and then exactly and
you'll continue training your model and
then deploy it from there okay that's
that's a good summary so so I think
we've done a pretty great job of what de
learning is and what licks are an a some
bring to the table in 65 minutes but if
there was one thing you'd like a
software engineer to remember from our
show what would you like that to be yeah
I think what I would like people to
remember is that the Elixir machine
learning ecosystem is much more complete
and competitive with the python
ecosystem than I would say people
presume you can do a ton with a little
in The Elixir ecosystem so you don't
necessarily need to depend on external
Frameworks and and Library or external
ecosystems and languages in The Elixir
ecosystem you can kind of live in the
stack and punch above your weight if you
will excellent was there anything we
missed in our example or introduction
that you'd like to add or anything at
all no I think that's pretty much it for
me if you want to learn more about the
Elixir machine learning ecosystem
definitely check out my book machine
learning and elixir from the pragmatic
bookshelf Sean thank you for coming on
the show it's been a real pleasure this
is Gavin Henry for software engineering
radio thank you for listening thanks for
having
me thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by it
e software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under creative
comments license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]